嘿, 你们好
hey, what's up guys
我是Cherno, 欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
my name is Cherno, and welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么, 今天, 我们要讨论的都是统一变量
so, today, we're going to be talking all about uniforms
一般来说, OpenGL或显卡中的统一变量是什么
what is a uniform in OpenGL or in graphics pro army in general
它们的用途是什么, 以及在OpenGL中是如何工作的
what are they used for, and how do they work in OpenGL
那么首先, 统一变量是一个非常单一的概念
so first of all, uniforms are a pretty single concept
它们基本上对于我们来说, 就是一种方式, 为了
they're basically just a way for us to
实际上从CPU端获取数据
actually get data from the kind of CPU side of things
那么在这个例子中, 是从c++到我们的着色器
so from c++, in this case, into our shader
所以我们实际上把它当一个变量使用
so we can actually use it like a variable
那么一个真不错的关于那个的例子
so a really good example of that
我们今天就直接进入到一些代码中
we're just going to just jump into some code straight away today
一个真不错的关于这个的例子是在我们的颜色应用中
a really good example of this is in our color application
我正好为你们运行一下那个, 为了恢复你们的记忆
if I just run that for you guys, for refresh your memory
我们在这里绘制了一个蓝色的正方形或矩形
we have a blue kind of square or rectangle that we're actually drawing over here
如果我们看看着色器的代码
if we take a look at the shader code
我们实际上得到那个蓝色的方式
the way that we're actually getting that blue color
只是通过在这儿硬编码一个颜色
is just by hard coding a color here
增加0.2的红色, 0.3的绿色和0.8的蓝色, 以及一个1的透明度
rise 0.2 red, 0.3 green, and 0.8 blue, with a 1.0 alpha
现在, 如果我们能在CPU端定义这些数据, 那就太好了
now, it would be great, if we could somehow define this data in the CPU side of things so on
在我们实际的c++中, 甚至可能在必要时更新那个
in our actual c++, and possibly even updated as necessary
那么好消息就是我们可以那样做
so the good news is we can do that
并且这儿有两种实现那个的主要方法
and there's two main ways of doing that
我们今天先看看统一变量
today we're going to look at uniforms
而这也是可能的, 正如你们可能从顶点那期视频中看到的
but it's also possible, as you guys could probably tell from the vertex kind of video
我们实际上也可以将数据从CPU传输到显卡
it's also possible for us to actually get data from CPU to the GPU
通过一个顶点缓冲区
via a vertex buffer
因此如果你们还没看过那个视频, 一定要去那边看看
and if you guys haven't seen that video, definitely check that out over there
但我们今天要关注统一变量
but today we're going to be focusing on uniforms
其实我打算做一个对比属性和统一变量的视频
I'm actually planning to make a comparison video between attributes and uniforms
因为这些是
because those are kind of
获取每个我们从CPU到显卡绘制的对象数据的两种主要方式
the two main ways of getting data kind of per object kind of that we're drawing from the CPU to the GPU
但今天又明确是关于统一变量的
but today again explicitly about uniforms
所以在这两者之间进行小小的比较
so in terms of just comparing the two lightly
你确实必须知道的比较大的区别就是, 统一变量是设置每次绘制的
the big thing that you do have to know is that uniforms are set per draw
所以基本上你可以设置一个统一变量
so basically you can set a uniform up
在你调用glDrawElements或glDrawArrays之前
before you call glDrawElements or glDrawArrays
或者任何你实际用来绘制的函数
or whatever you're using to actually do the drawing
而属性实际上是设置每个顶点的
whereas attributes are actually set kind of per vertex
所以, 换句话说, 你可以明显看到这里的位置属性
so, in other words, you can see that obviously the position attribute we have here
理论上来说, 可以是任意类型的数据
which theoretically could be any kind of data
在这里, 虽然它是一个位置
in this case, though it's a position
这就是每个顶点
this is per vertex
而关于统一变量, 我们可以在实际绘制之前设置它们
whereas with uniforms, we kind of set them before we do the actual drawing
所以它们是设置每次绘制的
so they're set per draw
这确实是一个比较大的区别
there's a really big difference
并且我们也会在专门的视频中进一步探讨那个
and again we'll explore that more in the dedicated video about that
那么让我们把这个颜色转换成可以c++中设置的一些参数吧
so let's convert this color into being something that we set from c++
所以实际上我首先要做的就是修改我的着色器
so the first thing I'm actually going to do is modify my shader
来到我的着色器文件, 并且看到这个片段着色器
I'm going to go into my shader file here, and into this fragment shader
我要添加一些代码, 实际上就在我们这里的输出代码下面
I'm going to add some code, so just underneath this output that we actually have here
我要写uniform vec4 u_Color
I'm going to write uniform vec4 u_Color
现在我想在这里使用一些命名约定
now I'd like to use a bit of a naming convention here
我真的不想使用一个构造碎片或其他
I didn't really use a fabric piece or anything
但随着我们接触统一类型
but as we get into uniforms
我要开始用它了
I'm going to start using it
基本上, 任何以u_开头的变量都是一个统一变量
basically, anything that begins with u_ is an actual uniform variable
而在这个例子中
and in this particular case
实际上这对于我来说还是有必要的
it's actually necessary for me to
区分这个变量和那个实际输出的color变量
differentiate this variable from of course the variable there's an actual output color
所以这就是我在着色器中所要做的, 就是这样
so that's all I have to do in my shader, that's it
我已经声明了一个统一变量
I've declared a uniform
我现在可以在我的着色器代码中使用这个统一变量
I can now use this uniform throughout my shader code
实际上, 我要做的是用像这样的u_Color替换这个color
and in fact what I'm going to do is replace this color with u_Color like this
所以我们基本上
so we're basically
把我们实际的矩形的每一像素每一片段的颜色都设置成
assigning the output color of each fragment of each pixel of our actual rectangle
这个统一变量实际的值
to be whatever this uniform value actually is
那么现在剩下的就是从C++中设置那个统一变量
so now all that's left to do is to actually set that uniform from c++
而在这儿的第二个问题就是变量的生存期
so the two things that matter here are the time of variable
就是这个作为组件矢量的vec4, 当你想起它和它的名称时
which the vec4 for component vector, when you remember that as well as the name
就是像那样的u_Color
so u_Color like that
好了, 让我们回到项目来设置这个
okay, let's go back to application and set this up
那么我会在我实际绑定的着色器后面去做, 对吧
so what I'm going to do is after my shader is actually bound, right
所以实际上我这里就是glUseProgram
so I've actually called glUseProgram
在你实际做这个的时候, 必须有一个实际绑定的着色器
you have to have a shader that's actually bound, when you actually do this
这样它才会知道标准输出到哪个着色器
so that it knows which which shader to standard out to
我要在这儿做的就是调用glUniform
what I'm going to do here is called glUniform
那么然后我们就有各种各样的函数
and then we have a variety of functions
你们实际上可以在文档中看看
that you guys can actually check out in the documentation
基本上在这儿的区别就是我们实际常设的数据类型
basically the difference here is the type of data that we're actually standing
以及我们有多少个组件
and how many components we have
那么我们可以发送多少浮点数
so how many how many floats are we sending
或者我们可以发送多少整数
or how many integers are we sending
现在, 在这个例子中, 我们知道它是一个vec4类型的
now, in this case, we know it's a vec4
它是有四个分量的
which is a four component kind of
基本上就是四个浮点数
which is basically just four floats
所以我们需要选用glUniform4f
so we need to choose glUniform4f
好了, 那么4是因为它们有4个
okay, so four because there's four of them
以及f是因为它们是浮点型
and f because they're floats
在这儿的第一个参数是这个变量的位置
the first parameter here is the location of this variable
以及你可以看到它实际上是一个整型
and you can see it is actually an int
所以在我们调用这个之前需要做的
so what we need to do before we even call this
实际上就是获取这个变量的位置
is actually retrieve the location of this variable
所以OpenGL所做的就是如何创建着色器
so what OpenGL does is once how shader gets created
每个统一变量基本上都有一个id
every uniform basically gets assigned an id
这样我们就可以引用它了
so that we can then reference it
而我们查找id的方式通常是通过它的名称
and the way that we look up that id typically is by its name
所以我们基本上就是问我们的着色器
so we can basically ask our shader
嘿, 这个u_Color变量
hey, this u_Color variable
请告诉我那个变量的位置
please tell me what the location of that variable is
而然后我们会得到一个整数
and then we'll get a integer back
在更现代的OpenGL版本中, 你实际上可以设置和索引
in more modern versions of OpenGL, you can actually set and index
就和我们实际设置这个layout(location=0)是一样的
kind of the same way that we that we're actually setting this layout location equals zero
所以你可以从 OpenGL 4.3 开始指定一个明确的统一变量位置
so you can specify an explicit uniform location starting with OpenGL 4.3
因此, 这是一种非常现代的新功能
so it is quite a modern kind of new feature
这就是为什么我不太喜欢用它的原因
which is why I don't really like using it too much
而在这个例子中, 我们就使用名称来获取它
and in this case, we're just going to retrieve it by using the name
因为那很好
because that's fine
那么当我回到应用
so if we go back to application
我要写的就是int location=glGetUniformLocation()
what I'm going to do is just write int location equals glGetUniformLocation
然后, 我们指定我们的着色器(shader)程序
and then we specify the program which is our shader
以及我们尝试获取的统一变量的名称
as well as the name of the uniform we're trying to retrieve
那么在这个例子中, 它就是u_Color
so in this case, it's u_Color
确保你清楚地拼写了这个
make sure that you obviously spell this
并使用与着色器中实际变量名完全相同的大小写
and use the exact same casing as you do with the actual variable name in your shader here
因为如果你不这样做, 那就不会得到
because if you don't, then it's not going to work out
现在, 我们有一个ASSERT宏, 我将在这里使用它
now, we do have an assert macro, I'm going to use it here
只要断言location不等于-1
and just assert that location does not equal -1
如果我们得到了-1, 它意味着没有找到我们的统一变量
if we get the location -1, it means that it could not find our uniform
现在这实际上可能是可以的
now that actually might be okay
因为你可能还没意识到
because what you might not realize immediately
就是那并不意味着你一定犯了错误
is that that doesn't mean necessarily that you've made an error
或者你的统一变量名称有拼写错误之类的
or that you've made a spelling mistake or something like that with your actual uniform name
如果在整个着色器中不使用那个统一变量
if you don't use that uniform throughout your shader
那么在着色器中实际存在那个统一变量
so you have that uniform actually present in your shader
但是它没被用过
but it's unused
然后OpenGL将在编译着色器时就会去掉那个
then OpenGL will just strip that when it compiles the shader
所以这实际上可能返回-1
so this might actually return -1
因为这个统一变量已经被删除了, 它没有被使用
because the uniform has been removed, it it's been unused
所以, 你不一定希望, 就像你知道的, 出现错误或程序崩溃
so, you don't necessarily want to, like you know, write out error or crash your program
如果它没有找到你的统一变量
if it doesn't find your uniform
可能是因为你已经重写了这个着色器
because you might have just rewritten the shader
忘记了移除它
and maybe you forgotten to remove it
或者也许你后面需要它等等
or maybe you want it for later or whatever
所以请记住这一点
so just keep that in mind
在这个例子中, 我只是断言它, 因为我确实真的
in this case, I'm just asserting it, because I do actually
我确实打算用它
I do actually plan on using it
我不想确保那个
I don't want to make sure that
事实上, 我做的一切都是对的
I've actually done everything correctly
所以现在我们有了一个位置, 我将把它输入这里, 这是第一个参数
so now that we have a location, I'm going to feed that into here, that's the first parameter
然后你可以看到我们需要设置四个浮点数
and then you can see that we need to set four floats
那么第一个浮点数就是0.2f
so the first one float I'm going to set is 0.2f
然后是0.3f, 基本上就和我之前设置的一样
then 0.3f, basically the same code that i have before
然后是0.8f和1.0f
then 0.8f and 1.0
所以我已经有效地将代码从着色器移到c++中
so i've effectively moved my code from the shader into c++
而最后, 我要把它写进位置调用
and finally i'm just gonna wrap this into location call
以及在GLCall宏中调用这个glUniform为了保证我们不会出错
and this glUniform call in my GLCall macro to make sure we don't have any errors
好了, 那么总结一下
all right, so to summarize
我通过使用实际的着色器id编写glUseProgram来绑定着色器
I'm binding my shader by writing glUseProgram with that actual shader id
获取这个实际颜色变量的位置
I'm retrieving the location of this actual color variable
而然后当得到那个位置时
and then once I've retrieved that location
我就用那个位置整数和这个值调用glUniform4f
I'm calling glUniform4f with that location integer as well as the value
这样我就可以在着色器中设置我的数据
so that I actually set my data in my shader
而在着色器中, 我所做的就是
and in the shader, all I've done is
通过输入关键字uniform以及类型和名称来创建统一变量
created a uniform by typing the keyword uniform along with the type and the name
就像任何其他变量一样
just like any other variable
实际上我用我的统一变量来写输出颜色
and I'm using my uniform here to actually write to the output color
那么如果一切顺利
so if everything goes correctly
我应该将这个颜色值写入我的实际输出颜色
I should be writing this color value into my actual output color
在这个程序中, 为了我的矩形的每一个像素
for every single pixel in my rectangle lips on this program
你可以看到, 我们得到了和以前完全相同的结果
and you can see, we get the exact same result as before
太完美了, 它起作用了
so perfect, it's working
我们会做的另一件事是检查
one other thing that we can do to check
因为很明显我在这里用的是同一种颜色
just because obviously I am using the same color here
我将把红色通道改为0.8f
I'll just change the red channel to be 0.8f
所以我们这里应该有更多的粉红色
so we should get much more of a pink color here
而你可以看到, 就在那里, 完美
and you can see, there it is, perfect
好了, 那么现在做点更令人兴奋的事情吧
okay, so now this is something a little bit more exciting
实际上让我们让这个颜色动起来, 并在渲染循环中随时间改变它
let's actually animate this color, and change it over time in our rendering loop
所以回到这里, 我基本上就是设置这个统一变量, 对吧
so back over here, I'm going to basically just set this uniform, right
在我绘制实际的矩形之前
before I draw my actual rectangles
所以我会把代码复制粘贴到这里
so I'll copy and paste this code over here
我将创建一个浮点数r, 这将是我们的红色通道
I'll make the float called r, which will be our red channel
我首先把它设置为0.0
I'll set that equal to 0.0 to begin with
我将输入r变量代替0.8f作为红色通道
I'm going to feed in that r variable instead of 0.8f as the red channel
然后我将添加一点记录来让它动起来
and then I'll just add a little bit of logging to animate it
所以我要做的一件事, 是将我的increment初始为0.05f
so one thing I'm going to do here, is set my increment to be 0.05f to begin with
如果我的r大于1.0f
if my r value is greater than 1.0f
我实际就会把increment设置成-0.05f
I'm actually going to set my increment to be -0.05f
否则如果r小于0
otherwise if r is less than 0
我就会把increment设置成0.05f
I'm going to set my increment to be positive 0.05f
我不想费心固定或诸如此类的事情
I'm not going to bother clamping or anything like that
因为这只是一个测试
because this is just a test really
而最后就是 r+=increment
and then finally r plus equals increment
所以, 对于红色通道, 应该做的基本上就是在1和0之间抖动
so what the should do is basically just bounce between one and zero for the red channel
那么让我们运行这个吧
so let's run this
你们可以看到, 我们在这里看到的是一个非常有派对风格的矩形
and you can see what we get here is a very party mode looking rectangle
变化得非常非常快
going very very quickly
因为我们实际上并没有限制帧速率
because we're not actually limiting our frame rate
那我们就尝试去做吧
so let's have a go up doing that
我要做的是向上滚动到这里, 我们实际创建窗口的位置
what I'm going to do is scroll up here to where we actually create our window
我要做的
and what I'm going to do
当我们在一个OpenGL上下文中, 就是设置这个glfwSwapInterval(1)
once we have an OpenGL context, is just set the glfwSwapInterval to one
这应该同步我们的V-Sync(垂直同步)
which should just synchronize this with our V-Sync
或者我们的主频刷新率, 对我来说是60
or otherwise our master's refresh rate, which for me is 60
那么让我们按f5
so let's hit f5
你可以看到, 我们得到了一个更平滑的动画
and you can see we get a much smoother animation here
差不多就是这样
and that's pretty much it
这就是OpenGL中的统一变量, 这就是如何使用它们
that's what uniforms are in OpenGL, that's how you use them
这真的很简单
it's really really simple
当然, 在这个例子中, 我们只使用了四个浮点数作为示例
of course in this case, we're just using four floats as an example
但实际上, 你可以使用任何数据类型
but you can use really any data type
或者你需要的任何数量的组件
or any kind of number of components that you need to
比如浮点数, 整数, 矩阵等等
so floats, integers, matrices all of that stuff
将来肯定会更多地参与其中
will definitely be getting into that a lot more in the future
统一变量是图形编程和OpenGL等的重要组成部分
uniforms uniforms are a really vital part of graphics programming and of OpenGL and all that
所以随着我们开始构建的越来越多
so as we actually start to build more and more
我们将一直使用它们
we'll be using them all the time
但你需要记住的真正重要的事情是
the really big thing that you need to keep in mind though
那统一变量实际上是每次绘制的
is that uniforms are actually per draw
所以很明显, 我们设置了uniform4f, 然后我们绘制了整个几何体
so obviously we set uniform4f, and then we draw our entire piece of geometry
在这个例子中只是一个矩形
which in this case is just a rectangle
所以它们实际上是独立的OpenGL
so they are actual separate OpenGL course
所以我们当然不能以任何方式找到统一变量或改变统一变量
so of course we can't in any way to find uniforms or change uniforms
正如我所说的
such as I say
在这两种绘制之间, 所以如果我
in between kind of drawing this, so if I had
所以很明显, 这绘制了两个三角形
so this gets obviously drawing two triangles
我不能用一种颜色绘制一个
I can't draw one of them with one color
而另一个用其他颜色
and one with the other color
如果是这样设置的话
if it's set up this way
因为在这个时候, 他们实际上是在一个绘制指令中一起绘制的
because at this point in time, they're actually being drawn together in one DrawCall
并且统一变量是设置每次绘制的
and uniforms are set per draw
如果我真的需要构成正方形的两个三角形中的一个
if I actually one of those two triangles that make up our square to
实际是不同颜色
actually be different colors
我需要通过顶点属性来实现这一点
I would need to do that via a vertex attribute essentially
并且我们将来肯定会讨论这个的
and we can definitely talk about that in the future
不管怎样, 希望你们喜欢这个视频
anyway, hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你喜欢的话, 就点击那个喜欢按钮
if you did, hit that like button
你也可以在这个渠道上支持这个系列以及我所做的一切
you can also support this series and everything that I do here on this channel
通过转到patreon.com/TheCherno
by going over to patreon.com/TheCherno
你可以访问这些OpenGL视频的所有源代码
you'll get access to all the source code for these OpenGL videos
以及一些其他激动人心的奖励, 你可以通过链接查看
as well as some other exciting rewards which you can check out by going to the link
discord是我喜欢宣传的另一件很酷的事情
discord is another really cool thing that I like to promote
因为基本上discord就是一个社区
because there's basically what discord is as a community of people
你可以讨论
with which you can talk about
所有OpenGL的东西或任何其他编程的东西
all the OpenGL stuff or any other programming stuff
所以discord就是TheCherno.discord
so discord TheCherno bumps such discord
我总是把网址弄错
I always get that url wrong
去TheCherno.com/discord并加入那个服务
go to TheCherno.com/discord and join that server
这真的很愉快, 你可以讨论这一期和所有的东西
it's a great time, you can discuss this episode and all of the stuff
这都是与编程有关的
that is related to programming
也许你在做一个项目
maybe you're working on a project
如果你需要一些帮助, 那是一个很好的去处
and you need some help, that's a great place to get it
下一次, 我们可能会继续讨论一些更的着色器的东西
next time, we're going to probably move on to some more upstanding shader stuff
我真的想开始把这些东西抽象出来
I really want to start kind of abstracting this stuff out
因为很重要我们必须
and because we'll essential we'll have to
我们最终必须将这些代码迁移到类中
we'll have to eventually kind of move this code into classes
因为我们会重复使用很多
because we'll be reusing a lot of it
当我们真正开始绘制模型之类的东西的时候
when we actually get down to drawing models and all that stuff
所以, 这可能就是下一期的内容
so, that's probably what's gonna be in the next episode
还有一些其他的事情我肯定需要提到
there were a few other things that I definitely need to mention there
那么, 下次见, 拜
so, I will see you guys in the next video, goodbye